I am Shale.
I am presenting our work on consistency models in databases.
This is a jointed work with Andrea, Azalea and Philippa.
Consistency models in distributed key-value stores are hard to understand.
There are many proposals of consistency model definitions.
For example, there are well-known general axiomatic definitions,
which put constraints on the shape of graph-based states.
Other trace-based semantics
defines consistency models as properties over the entire traces.
Last, there are many reference implementations
and reference operational semantics for specific consistency models.
We proposed an interleaving operational semantics
that can be parametrised by consistency models.
Specifically, we focus on consistency models in distributed key-value stores.
We show that our definitions are correct with respect to axiomatic definitions.
Because of the operational features, we believe that
our semantics can be an interface for
verifying implementations of distributed key-values stores
and reasoning client programs.
The internal structure and state of a distributed system can be very complicated,
for example, common structures including replicated database or sharded database.
Those databases often allowed weak behaviours
because of temporarily out of synchronisation.
Yet, these details are not important to the users.
In our semantics, we use a global key-value store,
or a kv-store, to abstract the state of a distributed store.
Each key in a kv-store is associated with a list of abstract versions.
Particularly, each abstract version contains a value.
the writer who committed this value
and a set of readers.
A client of a distributed kv-store may not observe the entire global state.
For example, this client may only observe state from one replica.
We model this through a notion of client view,
which only contains partial information over the global kv-store.
We propose a standard interleaving semantics.
Our semantics is parameterised by a notion of execution test, ET.
It checks if a client is allowed to commit a transaction.
In our semantics, the notion of client view
helps us to reduce a transaction in one abstract step
instead of several small steps with fine-grained interleaving.
The key rule in our semantics is atomic transaction rule,
which describes how a client commits a transaction.
We will explain it in the following slides.
Each view corresponds to a local snapshot, which is a simple, plain key-value store.
It is the initial state for a transaction,
and the transaction will read from or write to the local snapshot before commit.
Here we make our first assumption,
the snapshot includes the latest observable versions.
This corresponds to the last-write-win resolution policy,
which has been used in many distributed key-value stores.
The semantics for executing commands of a transaction is straightforward
since it is local to the transaction.
To track the effect of a transaction, we collect a fingerprint, that is, a read-write set.
Note that we focus on consistency models that satisfy snapshot property
also known as atomic visibility.
Hence, the fingerprint only tracks the first read before any write per key,
and the last write per key.
In our increment example, the final fingerprint contains two operations,
write 2 to key, k, and read 1 from key, k.
Now the client wants to commit the fingerprint to the kv-store.
But before that, we need to check if it is allowed.
We use a can-commit predicate to check, given a kv-store K and a view u,
if a fingerprint is allowed to commit under an execution test ET.
Recall that an execution test corresponds to a consistency model.
We will explain the execution test later.
Let assume that the check passes for now.
If the check passes.
We are ready to commit the fingerprint.
We pick a fresh transaction ID, for example t3.
For any write in the fingerprint, it appends a new version
with the writer to be the new transaction ID.
For read, it adds the transaction ID to the reader set.
However, we have not done yet.
We still need to decide a new view for the client.
Note that this new view will affect future transactions.
It is done thought a view-shift predicate
that is also parameterised by an execution test ET.
For example, the predicate here says the new view, u’, must contain all versions
included in the old view, u, and any new versions written by the transaction,
for example the last version here.
Note that all the steps I just described is one big rule in our semantics
called atomic transaction rule.
Other rules such as sequential composition are as expected.
In the atomic transaction rule, we mentioned two predicates,
can-commit and view-shift.
Both are parametrised by an execution test ET.
We use these two predicates to specify many well-known consistency models,
for example, causal consistency, snapshot isolation and parallel snapshot isolation.
Can-commit determines that given a view, u,
if the fingerprint, F, of a transaction is allowed to commit to the kv-store, K.
We will use the running example to explain the can-commit.
View-shift determines the post-view of the client after committing a transaction.
View-shift is easier to understand.
It often says something like
the post-view must include all versions previously observed by the same client
or versions written by the same client.
To explain can-commit, first,
we need to introduce some relations between transaction identifiers in the kv-store.
We have write-write, WW,
saying that one transaction commits a newer version on the same key
after another transaction.
Write-read, WR, says that a transaction directly reads from
the version written by another transaction.
Read-write, RW,
says that a transaction reads a version being overwritten by another translation.
Last, we have session order, which is the commit order of
transactions from the same client.
Can-commit is defined as closure property against a relation, R,
which will be a combination of the four relations I just introduced.
Here, we take causal consistency as an example
to show what we mean by a view is closed.
Assume the kv-store, K, we saw before.
Assume another client whose view only contains the first and last versions.
Causal consistency requires that
view is closed with respect to session order union write-read.
In the kv-store, we observe that there is a write-read edge
from transaction t1 to transaction t2.
The closure requires that
(1) if a view includes a version written by a transaction, for example, t2 here,
(2) if there is another transaction related to t2 with respect to the relation,
for example t1 here.
Then the view also needs to include all versions written by transaction t1.
Here the view needs to include the second version specifically.
If the client also includes the second version, we have a view that is closed
with respect to session order union write-read,
which corresponds to causal consistency.
Here is a table of all consistency models we have covered in the paper,
including causal consistency, CC, parallel snapshot isolation PSI,
snapshot isolation SI and serialisibility SER.
To justify our semantics
and particularly definitions of consistency models using execution tests.
We prove our operational definitions of consistency models is equivalent to
the well-known graph-based axiomatic definitions on abstract executions.
We prove it by trace equivalent.
The challenge here is that
abstract execution maintains a total commit order over all transactions,
while in our kv-store we only have a partial order over versions per key.
In abstract execution,
they define consistency models as constraints on visibility edges.
For each consistency model, we show an equivalent relation
between execution test, ET and constraints on visibility edges.
We then plug the relation into constructors,
which lifts the equivalent relation to single-step level,
that is, given an equivalent kv-store K and abstract execution X,
after one step, the result K’ and X’ are still equivalent.
The notion of equivalence between K and X means
they contain the same information.
Given the single-step equivalence, we can easily lift them into
an equivalent relation between traces.
Given our semantics, we have two applications.
One is to verify implementation by trace refinement.
We show how to do that for a particular replicated database
and a particular sharded database.
The challenge is to link the synchronisation mechanism in the implementations
to the view and closure mechanism in our semantics.
We also show how to use our semantics to reason about client programs,
by proving the invariant properties of reachable states of the client programs.
For example we can prove robustness.
Robustness can be done also in other semantics.
Here we provide a state-based invariant that implies robustness.
Second, we prove the mutual exclusion property of a lock program.
This property may be difficult to achieve in other graph-based semantics,
since they need to recover state from the graph.
While it is relatively easier to prove in  our semantics.
To conclude, we propose an interleaving operational semantics
which can be parametrised by consistency models.
We use global abstract kv-stores
to represent the detail states of distributed key-value stores.
This representation contains enough information
to allow us to specify many well-known consistency models.
We use views to represent the observable states of individual clients.
It also plays the key role in our semantics:
First, it allows us to have a standard interleaving operational semantics
on the level of transaction as an atomic step.
Second, it allows to model many weak consistency models.
Then we propose execution tests as operational definitions of consistency models.
We give many examples, including causal consistency and snapshot isolation.
We show that these operational definitions are equivalent
to the well-known axiomatic definitions.
All the trace-equivalent proofs are non-trivial
but we provide several levels of general constructors,
so we only need to focus on the equivalent relation
between execution tests and visibility constraints.
Our semantics can be an interface for verifying implementation
and reasoning client programs.
Although our semantics is very abstract,
we still manage to prove two implementation protocols.
The biggest strength of our semantics is that
it is state-based with interleaving on transaction level.
This is how most programmers think of the interaction to a key-value store.
In our second application, we show that
our semantics can prove state-based invariant properties of client programs.
In the future, it will be nice to first mechanise  our semantics
and build an engine that actually executes our semantics.
With the engine, it is possible to generate litmus tests for implementation,
and to build a model checker for client reasoning.